Harvard University, Graduate School of Design. The GSD History Collection, Administrative Affairs: An Inventory
Harvard University, Graduate School of Design. The GSD History Collection, Administrative Affairs: An Inventory
1936-1993
Special Collections, Frances Loeb Library, Graduate School of Design, Harvard University
DES.2009.0002.011762440
Harvard University, Graduate School of Design.
24 linear feet
Extent is approxmimate
This collection includes documents relating to the organization and administration of Harvard's Graduate School of Design, mainly between 1936 and 1993.
Acquisition Information
The material in this collection was assembled throughout the years in Robinson Hall, and later in Gund Hall.
Conditions on Use and Access
Contact the Special Collections Department, Frances Loeb Library, Graduate School of Design, Harvard University. Some folders may be restricted for a diversity of reasons, including internal Harvard University policies. Written request and permission from the librarian and/or dean may be required.
History
The first academic degree programs in architecture and landscape architecture at Harvard emerged from design education initiatives that began in 1874 when Charles Eliot Norton introduced architectural history into his fine arts courses. The first Harvard course devoted exclusively to architecture was offered by Herbert Langford Warren in 1893. In 1899 the first Harvard building devoted solely to instruction in the fields of design was started in memory of Nelson Robinson, Jr., a former Harvard student who had been interested in architectural design and landscape architecture. The Faculty of Architecture was established in 1914 to coordinate the curricula and degrees in architecture and landscape architecture. City planning became the third component of the design curriculum in 1909, when James Sturgis Pray began teaching planning courses within the landscape architecture program. It was not until 1936 that Harvard created a separate professional school for these various disciplines when the Graduate School of Design was established for the study of architecture, landscape architecture, and city planning. Joseph Hudnut was appointed dean of the newly established GSD, and he invited Walter Gropius to come to Harvard as chairman of the department of architecture in 1936. Another landmark during this period was the admission of women to the GSD for the first time in 1942. The postwar era brought enormous changes for all three professions. Both Hudnut and Gropius reached retirement age in the early 1950s, and Josep Lluis Sert was appointed dean in 1953. Among his many contributions was the establishment in 1960 of the first degree program in urban design in the United States.
This collection documents aspects relating to the organization and administration of the school. Materials include official registers, directories, news and press releases, and materials related to publications, exhibitions, conferences, lectures, and special events. It also includes some alumni association materials, library and building facilities, and GSD life photographs. The vast majority of the materials span the years 1936-1993.
The collection GSD History Collection: Administrative Affairs is arranged into six series: Series A (Administration); Series B (External Relations); Series C (Publications and Exhibitions); Series D (Events); Series E (Library and Building Facilities); Series F (GSD Life: Memorabilia and Photographs).
Series A (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: Administration) is comprised of Subseries AA: General Administration; Subseries AB: Official Registers and Registrar's Office Materials.
Series B (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: External Relations) is comprised of Subseries BA: News and Announcements; Subseries BB: Development; Subseries BC: Alumni Relations; and Subseries BD: Student Forum.
Series C (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: Publications and Exhibitions) is comprised of Subseries CA: GSD Publications; Subseries CB: GSD Publications -- Miscellaneous Materials; Subseries CC: GSD Exhibitions: Brochures, Posters, Exhibition Committees.
Series D (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: Events) is comprised of Subseries DA: Gund Hall Opening and Related Materials; Subseries DB: Special Events (Demonstrations, Celebrations, Anniversaries); Subseries DC: Conferences and Lectures).
Series E (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: Library and Building Facilities) is comprised of Subseries EA: Library; and Subseries EB: Building Facilities.
Series F (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: GSD Life, Miscellaneous and Photographs) is comprised of Subseries FA: Miscellaneous; and Subseries FB: Photographs.
- Series A: Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: Administration, / Date(s): 1960-1989 (bulk) -- 1935-2006 (inclusive); A000; / Quantity: 3 boxes / Dimensions: 3 linear ft. / Medium: varies / Support: varies
  Note: Series A (Harvard University GSD, Administrative Affairs: Administration) is comprised of Subseries AA: General Administration; Subseries AB: Official Registers and Registrar's Office Materials.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1935-2006; Subseries: AA000; / Quantity: 67 folders / Dimensions: 1.5 linear ft. / Medium: print; typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Subseries AA: General Administration is comprised of 67 folders (GSD History - Administrative. Boxes 1 and 1B) and contains papers related mainly to the dean's and faculty roles in the school's administration such as academic planning, and that of the visiting committee in school and program assessment.
    Local Note: Some folders may be restricted for a diversity of reasons. Written request and permission from the librarian and/or dean required.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1935-1936; Folder: AA001; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 9" x 6" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Reprint from the Report of the President of Harvard University, 1935-36: "Report of the School of Design for the Academic Year 1935-1936," by Dean Joseph Hudnut.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1980-1983; Folder: AA002; / Quantity: 3 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 4-1/2"; 11" x 6" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD telephone directories, 1980-1983.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1984; Folder: AA003; / Quantity: 5 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD Resources and Services, 1982-1984. Also includes a single page academic prospectus of the school issued by the Admissions and Financial Aid Office, 1982.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1983-1985; Folder: AA004; / Quantity: 5 items / Dimensions: 11" x 5-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD telephone directories, 1983-1985.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1985-1988; Folder: AA005; / Quantity: 7 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD telephone directories, 1985-1988.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1986; Folder: AA006; / Quantity: 10 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Listings of GSD non-teaching staff, a couple of GSD NewsNote flyers, and staff appointment notices.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1985-1987; Folder: AA007; / Quantity: 3 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD staff handbooks, 1985-1987.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1984-1988; Folder: AA008; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD faculty and staff booklets.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1986-1987; Folder: AA009; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD staff handbooks, 1986-1987.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1970s; Folder: AA010; / Quantity: 4 items / Dimensions: 9" x 4" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Prospectuses / brochures about Harvard Graduate School of Design.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1969-1972; Folder: AA011; / Quantity: 47 items / Dimensions: varies / Medium: print; copies; typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Press releases and clippings pertaining the history of the GSD, 1970-1972. Includes "School of Design Threatened with Critical Deficit" (Harvard Gazette), and "Design Professors Seek Dean's Ouster" (The Harvard Crimson).
    Note: Also included are xerographic copies of photographs of Gund Hall during construction, and two typescripts, one entitled The School Today, the other The School in the Future.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1970; Folder: AA012; / Quantity: 9 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Architecture Study Committee: Report to the Provost, 1970. Cornell University.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1954-1955; Folder: AA013; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8" x 5-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Copy of Harvard University, The President's Report, 1954-1955.
    Citation note: Previously filed under Rare Ref H261 pr 1954/1955.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1970; Folder: AA014; / Quantity: 4 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Four copies of the announcement of Maurice Kilbridge's deanship at the GSD. Includes press release.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1980-1981; Folder: AA015; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, and Student Handbook, for the academic year 1980-1981.
    Local Note: This folder is restricted. Written request and permission required, as indicated in AA000.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1983; Folder: AA016; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1982-1983.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1981-1984; Folder: AA017; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print; typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Background materials related to the history of the GSD. Includes GSD News and GSD News Note, appointment announcements, as well as typescripts (working papers) related to academic planning: "The Mission of the Graduate School of Design" and "The Range and Focus of GSD Degree Programs."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1983-1988; Folder: AA018; / Quantity: 64 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Typescript, notes, and memos on academic planning, 1988, including a multi-year financial plan, 1983-1984.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1991; Folder: AA019; / Quantity: 39 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Current Conditions and Academic Planning Issues: Discussion Paper by Gerald M. McCue, prepared as background material for the GSD's academic planning group. Also includes a summary of faculty comments about the report.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1987-1988; Folder: AA020; / Quantity: 35 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1987-1988, by Gerald McCue.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1986-1987; Folder: AA021; / Quantity: 32 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1986-1987, by Gerald McCue, with cover letter addressed to Harvard University President Derek Bok.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1985-1986; Folder: AA022; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1985-1986, by Gerald McCue,
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1980-1984; Folder: AA023; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1980-1984, by Gerald McCue. Also includes organization of faculty and their administrative assignments for the academic year 1984-1985.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1989-1990; Folder: AA024; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 11" x 8-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1989-1990, by Gerald McCue,
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 2003; Folder: AA025; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 11-1/2" x 6" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD Annual Report, Fiscal Year 2003.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 2005; Folder: AA026; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD Annual Report, 2005, produced by the Office of Development and Alumni/ae Relations, GSD.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 2006; Folder: AA027; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD Donor Report, 2006.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1967; Folder: AA028; / Quantity: 12 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript; manuscript / Support: paper
    Note: Appointment list for Dean Sert, maninly meeting with donor prospects, hand-annotated.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1984; Folder: AA029; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Schedule of activities for the National Architectural Accrediting Board (NAAB), visiting committee, February 1984.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982; Folder: AA030; / Quantity: 88 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: "Resumes of the Academic Staff" for year 1982. Includes resumes for Anthony Ames, Thomas A. Amsler, Marc Michel Angelil, Andrea Clark Brown, Jeffrey Clark, Henry N. Cobb, Stuart Earl Cohen, Caroline Brown Constant, Michael David Dennis, Peter D. Eisenman, Michael Flynn, Urs Peter Gauchat, Donald B. Genasci, Myron Goldsmith, Hans William Hagen, David Paltiel Handlin, Michael K. Kim, Susie Kim, Alfred H. Koetter, Andre C. Komorn, Alex Krieger, William J. Le Messurier, Ralph Lerner, Gerald Mallon McCue, Barbara Meri Littenberg, Noel Michael McKinnell, Robert J. Miklos, Robert Bradford Newman, Paul Stevenson Oles, Steven Kent Peterson, Bruno Pfister, Martha A. Pilgreen, Moshe Safdie, Daniel L. Schodek, Eduard F. Sekler, John Andrew Seiler, Robert Silver, Jorge Silvetti, Albert Szabo, Masami Takayama, Stanley Tigerman, Raimund Gerhard Vanderweil, Judith Wolin, Gary Wolf, Ilhan Zeybekoglu.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982; Folder: AA031; / Quantity: 88 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: "Course Descriptions" for year 1982.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982; Folder: AA032; / Quantity: 18 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: "Current GSD Catalog"; "Academic Policies and Procedures"; "Institutional Governance" for year 1982.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1981-1982; Folder: AA033; / Quantity: 1 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Annual Report, 1981-1982.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1983; Folder: AA034; / Quantity: 10 items / Dimensions: 5-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Series of booklets for the academic year 1982-1983 with GSD information: Frances Loeb Library Guide, GSD Facebook, GSD Fall Bulletin, GSD Faculty Directory, GSD Resources + Services, GSD Association Council, GSD Visiting Committee, GSD Loeb Fellows. Also includes a list of Visiting Faculty for the year 1982-1983
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1983; Folder: AA035; / Quantity: 11" x 11" items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Four issues of HGSD News, for the years 1982-1983.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1983; Folder: AA036; / Quantity: 5 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Typescripts, "Annual Giving Program Fellowship Fund" and "Major Capital Grants Committed to the Graduate School of Design."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1983; Folder: AA037; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 9-1/2" x 7-1/2"; 10-1/2" x 7-1/2" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Two small posters (lefalets) on Exhibitions and Lectures at the GSD for Fall 1982, and Spring 1983.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1981-1983; Folder: AA038; / Quantity: 4 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Several flyers, news notes, memos, press releases on renovations to Gund Hall, from 1981-1983. "Gund Hall Facilities Renovation Program", "Study for Renovation of Gund Hall Underway", and "Don M. Hisaka and Associates Selected to Undertake Gund Hall Repairs."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982; Folder: AA039; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 14" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: "Interview: Henry N. Cobb and Peter Eisenman" as published in Skyline, June 1982.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1978-1979; Folder: AA040; / Quantity: 35 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript; mimeograph copies / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Team Report, 1978-1979, with cover letter to President Bok (Harvard University) from NAAB (National Architectural Accrediting Board).
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1986-1988; Folder: AA041; / Quantity: 17 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: File includes several GSD NewsNote, newsletters with appointments made at the GSD, both of faculty and staff; as well as two exhibition brochures: "Werner Seligmann: Recent Works" and "Space Framed IV" (on the work of Geraldine Erman and Michael Gitlin).
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1986; Folder: AA042; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 18" x 11-1/2" / Medium: newsprint / Support: paper
    Note: Harvard University Gazzette Supplement, on occassion of the GSD's 50th anniversary; entitled "GSD at 50."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1995; Folder: AA043; / Quantity: 15 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Magazine, reprint, and several copies of an article "Space and Spirit", published in Harvard Magazine, authored by Craig Lambert and with photography by Heinrich Hermann.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1970-1971; Folder: AA044; / Quantity: 8 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Several articles, reprints, and clippings about Design Research (D|R), the store on Brattle Street, Cambridge, established by Benjamin Thompson.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1990-1991; Folder: AA045; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Dean's Report, 1990-1991.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1993; Folder: AA046; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript / Support: paper
    Note: Plan for the Graduate School of Design at Harvard University: A Progress Report, by Peter Rowe.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1993; Folder: AA047; / Quantity: 17 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: typescript; print / Support: paper
    Note: Memorandums about, and print copies of Official Register text used for the DDes program. Policy issues discussed.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1993; Folder: AA048; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: mimeograph copy / Support: paper
    Note: Outline for the design of a "Cover Design for a Long Playing Record Album" (for the Harvard Krokodiloes).
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1982-1987; Folder: AA049; / Quantity: 4 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: GSD Visiting Committee (for academic years 1982-1983; 1983-1984; 1986-1987). (These are not the committee's reports, they only include background of committee members.
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1995; Folder: AA050; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1995. Includes "Meeting Agenda", "A Plan for the Graduate School of Design at Harvard University: A Status Report", and "Biographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1997; Folder: AA051; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: A Plan for the Graduate School of Design at Harvard University: An Update, Future Activities and Further Needs by Peter Rowe, 1997. (Prepared as part of a university-wide academic planning activities).
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1991; Folder: AA052; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1991. Includes "Draft Agenda", "Biographies of Committee Members", 1990-1991 Annual Report", "Student Data" and "Press Clippings."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1993; Folder: AA053; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1993. Includes "Agenda", "Biographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1995; Folder: AA054; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1995. Includes "Meeting Agenda", "A Plan for the Graduate School of Design at Harvard University. A Status Report", and "Biographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1996; Folder: AA055; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1996. Includes "Meeting Agenda" and "Bibliographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1997; Folder: AA056; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1997. Includes "Meeting Agenda", "A Plan for the Graduate School of Design at Harvard University. An Update, Future Activities and Further Needs", and "Biographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1998; Folder: AA057; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1998. Includes "Meeting Agenda", "A Report to the Visiting Committee", "Description of Core Studios and Studio Options", "Biographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1999; Folder: AA058; / Quantity: 1 item / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Visiting Committee Meeting, 1999. Includes "Meeting Agenda" and "Biographies of Committee Members."
  - Subseries AA: General Administration, / Date(s): 1999; Folder: AA059; / Quantity: 2 items / Dimensions: 8-1/2" x 11" / Medium: print / Support: paper
    Note: Two copies of Visiting Committee Meeting, 1999. Includes "Meeting Agenda", "A Report to Visiting Committee", "List of Lecture Courses in History and Theory, Science and Technology, and Socioeconomic Studies", and "Biographies of Committee Members."